I have spent the past 38 years trying to be invisible.
لقد قضيت الـ38 عامًا المنصرمة وأنا أحاول أن أبقى غير مرئية.
I'm a copy editor.
أنا مراجعة لغوية.
I work at The New Yorker,
أعمل لصالح مجلة الـ"نيو يوركر".
and copyediting for The New Yorker is like playing shortstop
والمراجعة اللغوية لصالح الـ"نيو يوركر" تشبه عمل لاعب خط الوسط
for a Major League Baseball team:
لفريق كرة سلة من الدرجة الأولى في الدوري:
every little movement gets picked over by the critics --
حيث يتم رصد جميع تحركاتك من النقاد -
God forbid you should commit an error.
أن ترتكب خطأ لا قدر الله.
Just to clarify: copy editors don't choose what goes into the magazine.
للتوضيح فقط: المحررون اللغويون لا يختارون محتوى المجلة.
We work at the level of the sentence,
نحن نعمل على مستوى الجُملة،
maybe the paragraph,
ربما الفقرة
the words, the punctuation.
والكلمات وعلامات الترقيم.
Our business is in the details.
عملنا يكمن في التفاصيل،
We put the diaeresis, the double dot, over the "i" in "naïve."
نحن من يضع النقطتين فوق ال"i" في "naïve".
We impose house style.
نحن نفرض أسلوب المنشور.
Every publication has a house style.
لكل المنشور أسلوبها.
The New Yorker's is particularly distinctive.
الـ"نيو يوركر" متميزة على وجه الخصوص.
We sometimes get teased for our style.
يتهكمون علينا بسبب أسلوبنا أحيانا.
Imagine -- we still spell "teen-ager" with a hyphen,
تخيلوا -- لازلنا نكتب "teen-ager" (مراهق) بشرطة الوصل،
as if that word had just been coined.
كما لو كانت هذه الكلمة قد صيغت حديثًا.
But you see that hyphen in "teen-age"
عندما ترون شرطة الوصل في "teen-age"
and that diaeresis over "coöperate,"
والنقطتين فوق "coöperate،"
and you know you're reading The New Yorker.
تعرفون أنكم تقرأون مجلة نيويوركر.
Copyediting at The New Yorker is a mechanical process.
المراجعة اللغوية في "نيويوركر" هي عملية آلية.
There is a related role called query proofreading,
هناك دور مرتبط بالمراجعة يُسمى مراجعة النسخ المطبعية التجريبية،
or page-OK'ing.
أو صفحة الموافقات.
Whereas copyediting is mechanical,
فبينما تكون المراجعة اللغوية آلية،
query proofreading is interpretive.
فإن تصحيح التجارب المطبعية يتطلب مناقشة.
We make suggestions to the author through the editor
نقدم اقتراحات للمؤلف من خلال المحرر
to improve the emphasis of a sentence
ليحسن من وَقْع الجملة
or point out unintentional repetitions
أو الإشارة للتكرار غير المتعمّد
and supply compelling alternatives.
وندعم ذلك بالكلمات البديلة المناسبة.
Our purpose is to make the author look good.
وغرضنا هو جعل المؤلف يبدو في صورة حسنة.
Note that we give our proofs not directly to the author,
لاحظوا أننا لا نعطي تعديلاتنا مباشرة للمؤلف،
but to the editor.
لكن للمحرر.
This often creates a good cop/bad cop dynamic
وهذا يشبه الشرطي الجيد والشرطي السيء
in which the copy editor -- I'll use that as an umbrella term --
حيث يكون المحرر - سأستخدم هذا كمصطلح عام -
is invariably the bad cop.
دائما الشرطي السيء.
If we do our job well, we're invisible,
إذا قمنا بعمل جيد، فنحن غير مرئيون،
but as soon as we make a mistake,
لكن عندما نخطئ،
we copy editors become glaringly visible.
يصبح المحررون مرئيين علي نحو فاضح.
Here is the most recent mistake that was laid at my door.
وإليكم أحدث خطأ أتحمّله.
[Last Tuesday, Sarah Palin, the pre-Trump embodiment
[الثلاثاء الماضي، سارة بالين، والتي هي تجسيد لـ"ترامب"
of populist no-nothingism in the Republican Party,
في النزعة الشعوبية للا-لاشيء في الحزب الجمهوري،
endorsed Trump.]
أيَّدتْ "ترامب".]
"Where were The New Yorker's fabled copy editors?" a reader wrote.
"أين هم محررو جريدة النيويركر؟" يتساءل قارئ.
"Didn't the writer mean 'know-nothingism'?"
"ألا يقصد الكاتب يعلم-اللاشيء؟"
Ouch.
يا للخزي.
There's no excuse for this mistake.
ليس هناك من عذر لهذا الخطأ.
But I like it: "no-nothingism."
لكنني أحبها كما هي: "لا-لاشيء."
It might be American vernacular for "nihilism."
قد نعتبرها الكلمة العامية الأمريكية لـكلمة "العدمية."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Here, another reader quotes a passage from the magazine:
إليكم اقتباسًا من أحد القرّاء لمقطع من المجلة:
[Ruby was seventy-six, but she retained her authoritative bearing;
[روبي كانت في 76، لكنها حصلت على برائتها؛
only her unsteady gait belied her age.]
فقط المشية غير المستقرة هي التي تُكَذِب عمرها.]
He added:
أضاف القارئ:
"Surely, someone at The New Yorker knows the meaning of 'belied,'
"بالطبع، أحدهم في النيويوركر يعلم معني كلمة "تكذب،"
and that it is the opposite of how it is used in this sentence.
وأن هذا قد عكس معنى الجملة.
Come on! Get it together."
ما بكم! ركزوا."
Belie: to give a false impression.
يكذب: تعني إعطاء انطباع غير صحيح.
It should have been "betrayed."
كان يجب ان تكون الكلمة "تفضح."
E.B. White once wrote of commas in The New Yorker:
إ.ب. وايت كتب ذات مرة عن الفواصل في صحيفة نيويوركر:
"They fall with the precision of knives outlining a body."
إنها بحدة السكاكين التي تُقَطِع الجسد."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it's true -- we get a lot of complaints about commas.
وهذا صحيح- تصلنا العديد من الشكاوي بشأن الفواصل.
"Are there really two commas in 'Martin Luther King, Jr., Boulevard'?"
"هل هناك حقًا فاصلتين في اسم 'مارتن لوثر كنج، ج.، بولفارد'؟"
There may not be on the sign, but yes, that is New Yorker style for "Jr."
ربما لا توجد فواصل في توقيعه، لكن نعم هذا هو أسلوب الجريدة لكتابة "ج.،"
One wag wrote:
كتب أحدهم ساخرًا:
["Please, could you expel, or, at least, restrain,
[رجاءً، هل يمكنكم طرد، أو، على الأقل، توقيف،
the comma-maniac, on your editorial staff?"]
مهووس الفواصل، من فريق المحررين؟"]
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Ah, well.
آه، حسنًا.
In this case, those commas are well-placed,
في هذه الحالة، الفواصل مستخدمه بشكل جيد،
except that there should not be one
عدا أنه يجب أن لا توجد فاصلة
between "maniac" and "on."
بين كلمتي "مهووس الفواصل"و"من."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Also, if we must have commas around "at least,"
أيضًا، إذا كان لا بد من وضع فواصل حول كلمة "على الأقل،"
we might change it up by using dashes around that phrase:
علينا أن نغيرها باستخدام شرطة حول تلك العبارة:
"... -- or, at least, restrain --"
"..-أو، على الأقل، توقيف-"
Perfect.
أصبحت مثالية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Then there's this:
وهناك أيضًا هذه:
"Love you, love your magazine,
"أحبكم، أحب مجلتكم،
but can you please stop writing massive numbers as text?"
لكن رجاءً هل يمكنكم إيقاف استخدام أرقام ضخمة نصيًا؟"
[two and a half million ...]
[اثنان ونصف مليون...]
No.
لا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
One last cri de coeur from a spelling stickler:
مثال أخير: صرخة من القلب من أحد المدققين في التهجئة:
["Those long stringy things are vocal cords, not chords."]
[تلك الحبال الطويلة تسمي أحبالًا صوتية، ليست أوتارًا صوتية."]
The outraged reader added,
وأضاف القارئ الغاضب،
"I'm sure I'm not the first to write
"أنا متأكد أنني لست أول من يكتب
regarding this egregious proofreading error,
بخصوص هذا الخطأ المطبعي الفاضح،
but I'm equally sure I won't be the last.
وبالمثل إنني لن أكون الأخير.
Fie!"
اللعنة!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I used to like getting mail.
أنا أحببت دومًا تلقي البريد.
There is a pact between writers and editors.
هناك فرق بين الكُتّاب والمحررين.
The editor never sells out the writer,
المحرر لا يخون الكاتب أبدًا،
never goes public about bad jokes that had to be cut
لا يخبر العامة عن النكات السيئة التي تم محوها
or stories that went on too long.
أو القصص التي أطال فيها جدًا.
A great editor saves a writer from her excesses.
المحرر العظيم يحمي الكاتب من تجاوزاته.
Copy editors, too, have a code;
المراجع اللغوي، أيضًا، له مبدأ؛
we don't advertise our oversights.
نحن لا نعلن عما يتكشف لنا.
I feel disloyal divulging them here,
أنا أشعر بعدم إخلاصي بالحديث عنهم هنا،
so let's have look at what we do right.
ولذا لنأخذ نظرة على ما نفعله بشكل صحيح.
Somehow, I've gotten a reputation for sternness.
بطريقة ما، أنا معروفة بالصرامة.
But I work with writers who know how to have their way with me.
لكني أعمل مع كتاب يعرفون كيف يتعاملون معي.
I've known Ian Frazier, or "Sandy," since the early 80s.
أنا أعرف إيان فرازير أو "ساندي" منذ بداية الثمانينات.
And he's one of my favorites,
وهو من الفضلين لدي،
even though he sometimes writes a sentence
رغم أنه أحيانا يكتب جملة
that gives a copy editor pause.
يتوقف عندها المراجع اللغوي.
Here is one from a story about Staten Island
فهنا مثلا جملة من قصة عن جزيرة ستاتين
after Hurricane Sandy:
بعد إعصار ساندي:
[A dock that had been broken in the middle and lost its other half
[انكسر الميناء من منتصفه وضاع النصف الاخر
sloped down toward the water,
وانحدر إلى الماء،
its support pipes and wires leaning forward
ودعائمه من المواسير والأسلاك انزلقت للأمام
like when you open a box of linguine and it slides out.]
مثل فَتْحَك علبة معكرونة اسباجتي فتنزلق هذه خارجا.]
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This would never have got past the grammarian in the days of yore.
هذه العبارة لم تكن لتمر أبدا على النَحَويّ في الأيام الخالية.
But what could I do?
ما الذي باستطاعتي فعله؟
Technically, the "like" should be an "as,"
تقنيا، كلمة "تشبه" يجب تغييرها إلى "مثل،"
but it sounds ridiculous,
لكن هذا يبدو سخيفا،
as if the author were about to embark on an extended Homeric simile --
كما لو أن المؤلف كان على وشك الشروع في تشبيه شاعري عظيم-
"as when you open a box of linguine."
"مثل فتحك لعلبة معكرونة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I decided that the hurricane conferred poetic justice on Sandy
قررت أن الإعصار منح عدالة شاعرية ل"ساندي"
and let the sentence stand.
فلم يحطم الجملة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Generally, if I think something is wrong,
عموما، لو كنت أعتقد أن هناك شيء خاطئ،
I query it three times.
أستفسر عنه ثلاث مرات.
I told Sandy that not long ago in a moment of indiscretion and he said,
أخبرت ساندي بذلك منذ وقت ليس بالطويل في لحظة طيش فقال،
"Only three?"
"ثلاث فقط؟"
So, he has learned to hold out.
وبهذا، فقد تعلم أن يصبر عليّ.
Recently, he wrote a story for "Talk of the Town,"
مؤخرا، كتب قصة ل"حديث المدينة،"
that's the section at the front of the magazine
تلك الفقرة في واجهة المجلة
with short pieces on subjects ranging from Ricky Jay's exhibit
مع ملحوظات قصيرة عن مواضيع متنوعة ابتداءا بمعرض ريكي جاي
at the Metropolitan Museum
في متحف ميتروبوليتان
to the introduction of doggie bags in France.
وانتهاءا بمقدمة عن حقائب الكلاب في فرنسا.
Sandy's story was about the return to the Bronx
قصة ساندي كانت عن عودة
of Supreme Court Justice Sonia Sotomayor.
سونيا سوتوماير لمحكمة العدل العليا في برونكس.
There were three things in it that I had to challenge.
وهنا ثلاث أشياء علي حلها.
First, a grammar query.
أولا، مشكلة القواعد النحوية.
The justice was wearing black and Sandy wrote,
كانت العدالة ترتدي الأسود وكتب ساندي،
[Her face and hands stood out like in an old, mostly dark painting.]
[وجهها ويداها برَزَا مثل رسم قديم وداكن.]
Now, unlike with the hurricane,
الآن، على عكس قصة الإعصار،
with this "like," the author didn't have the excuse
كلمة "تشبه،" لم يكن للكاتب أي سبب
of describing hurricane damage.
لاستخدامها في وصف دمار الإعصار.
"Like" in this sense is a preposition, and a preposition takes an object,
"شبه" هنا حرف جر، يأتي بعده مفعول،
which is a noun.
أي الاسم.
This "like" had to be an "as."
كلمة "شبه"هنا يجب أن تكون كلمة "مثل."
"As in an old, mostly dark painting."
"مثل أن تكون في لوحة قديمة، داكنة"
Second, a spelling issue.
ثانيا، مسألة الهجاء.
The author was quoting someone who was assisting the justice:
المؤلف كان يقتبس من شخص يعمل في مجال العدالة:
["It will be just a minute.
["سيستغرق الأمر دقيقة فحسب.
We are getting the justice mic'ed,"]
نحن نُمَكرف القاضي،"]
Mic'ed?
نُمَكرِف؟
The music industry spells it "mic"
في مجال الموسيقي يُقال "مايك" ( مايكرفون)
because that's how it's spelled on the equipment.
لأن هذه هي طريقة تهجئة المعدات.
I'd never seen it used as a verb with this spelling,
لكنني لم أراها تستخدم أبداً كفعل بهذه التهجئة،
and I was distraught to think that "mic'ed"
واضطربت كثيرا لفكرة أن كلمة "نُمَكرِف"
would get into the magazine on my watch.
قد تنشر في مجلة تحت مراقبتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
New Yorker style for "microphone" in its abbreviated form is "mike."
أسلوب صحيفة النيويوركر لإختصار "ميكرفون"هو "مايك."
Finally, there was a sticky grammar and usage issue
أخيرا، كانت هناك مشكلة قاعدة نحوية بغيضة واستخدامها
in which the pronoun has to have the same grammatical number
حيث يجب على الضمير أن يكون مطابقا عددياً
as its antecedent.
لما سبقه.
[everyone in the vicinity held their breath]
[كل واحد في الجوار حبسوا نفَسَهم]
"Their" is plural and "everyone," its antecedent, is singular.
"هم" جمع و"كل واحد" التي سبقتها مفرد.
You would never say, "Everyone were there."
لا يمكنك أن تقول، "كل واحد كانوا هناك."
Everyone was there. Everyone is here.
كل واحد كان هنا.كل واحد يكون هنا.
But people say things like, "Everyone held their breath" all the time.
لكن الناس يقولون أشياء مثل، "الجميع يحبسون نفَسَهُم" طوال الوقت،
To give it legitimacy,
ولجعلها صحيحة،
copy editors call it "the singular 'their,'"
يطلق عليها المراجعون اللغويين "`هم`المفرد،"
as if calling it singular makes it no longer plural.
كما لو كان الإدعاء بأنها مفرد سيجعلها كذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It is my job when I see it in print to do my best to eliminate it.
إنها وظيفتي عندما أراها تُطبع أن افعل ما بوسعي لمحوها.
I couldn't make it, "Everyone held her breath,"
لم أستطع أن أجعلها، "كل واحد يحبس نفَسَهَا،"
or "Everyone held his breath,"
أو "كل واحد يحبس نفَسَهُ،"
or "Everyone held his or her breath."
أو "كل فرد يحبس نفَسَه أونفَسَها."
Whatever I suggested had to blend in.
أيا يكن ما أقترحه كان مرفوض.
I asked, through the editor,
سألتُ، المحرر،
if the author would consider changing it
إذا كان بإمكان المؤلف أن يغيرها
to "All in the vicinity held their breath,"
إلي "الكل في الجوار حبسوا نفَسَهم،"
because "all" is plural.
لأن "الكل" جمع.
Nope.
فلم يقبل.
I tried again: "All those present held their breath?"
حاولت ثانية: "كل الموجودين أمسكوا نفَسَهم؟"
I thought this sounded vaguely judicial.
ظننت أن هذا يبدو حكيما بشكل ما.
But the editor pointed out
لكن المحرر وضح لي
that we could not have "present" and "presence"
أننا لا يمكن أن نستخدم كلمتي "موجود" و "وجود"
in the same sentence.
في جملة واحدة.
When the final proof came back,
بإكتمال الطبعة التجريبية الأخيرة،
the author had accepted "as" for "like,"
الكاتب كان قد وافق على "مثل" بدل "تشبه،"
and "miked" for "mic'ed."
و "تزويد بالمايك" بدل "نُمَكرِف."
But on "Everyone held their breath," he stood his ground.
لكن بالنسبة لـ"كل واحد حبسوا نفَسَهم،" لم يُغيرها.
Two out of three isn't bad.
2 من 3 ليس سيئا.
In the same issue,
في نفس الموضوع،
in that piece on doggie bags in France,
في مقطع عن حقائب الكلاب في فرنسا،
there was the gratuitous use of the f-word by a Frenchman.
كان هناك استخدام غير مبرر لشتيمة من قِبل رجل فرنسي.
I wonder, when the mail comes in,
وتساءلت، عندما يأتي البريد،
which will have offended the readers more.
ما الذي سيُغضِب القراء أكثر (الشتيمة أم الأخطاء النحوية).
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)